Guide to the H. David Cogley Papers 1969-1970
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
H. David Cogley Papers
1969-1970
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 319
Cogley, H. David (Herbert David), 1945-
0.1 linear ft. and 1 partial reel microfilm
H. David Cogley was an engineer with the 326th engineer battalion of the 101st Airborne Division stationed at Camp Eagle in South Vietnam. His collection includes a scrapbook, reminiscences, and photographs of his experiences in South Vietnam as a member of an engineer battalion in the 101st Airborne Division from 1969 to 1970.
Biographical Note
Herbert David Cogley was born in New Orleans on December 28, 1945. At about one year of age he moved to the Brusett, Montana area. He earned his high school diploma in Jordan, Montana, in 1964. In 1968, Cogley earned a BS in Mechanical Engineering Technology from Montana State University. The same year, he gained a commission as a second lieutenant in the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers through the Reserve Officers Training Corps at Montana State University.
Cogley was stationed in Vietnam for one year, beginning in late 1969, as an engineer with the 326th engineer battalion of the 101st Airborne Division. In November 1970, he was released from active duty, whereupon he returned to the United States. Cogley went on to receive a JD in law at the University of Montana Law School in 1975. He served on the legal staff of the Montana Legislature from 1975 to 1989. Since 1979, he has been owner and manager of Wildwood Log Homes in Clancy, Montana.
Cogley has a wife, Helen, three sons and a daughter.
The collection includes a scrapbook, photographs, and two reminiscences of H. David Cogley's experiences in South Vietnam as a member of an engineer battalion in the 101st Airborne Division from 1969 to 1970.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Reminiscence, 1969-1970, 0.1 linear ft.
Series II: Vietnam Scrapbook, 1969-1970, 1 partial reel microfilm (55 frames)
Series III: Photographs, 1970, 50 items
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The materials in this collection remained with H. David Cogley until donation to the K. Ross Toole Archives.
Gift of H. David Cogley, 1972.
During original processing, fifty 35mm negatives and secondary photographic prints were separated from this collection and integrated into the K. Ross Toole Archives general photo collection. These negatives and prints were given photograph numbers 74-99 through 74-148. In 2003 the photographic materials were reintegrated with the paper materials.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Reminiscences; Scrapbooks; Photographs
Veteran--Montana -- Clancy; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Personal narratives, American; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Engineering and construction; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Veterans--Montana--Clancy
United States. Army. Airborne Division, 101st; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers. Engineer Battalion, 326th; United States. Army -- Officers
Photographs; Military
- Reminiscences, 1969-1970; Series I; 2 folders
  This series contains two items. The first is a 57-page typed reminiscence of H. David Cogley's experiences in Vietnam. The reminiscence includes a description of airmobile combat engineer unit projects and daily life, in addition to original poetry by Cogley. The reminiscence also includes four appendices: a glossary of Vietnam terms, a hand-rendered map of South Vietnam, a firebase inspection checklist, and an after action report. The second is a revised and spiral bound version of the reminiscence entitled "Vietnam Journal, 1969-1970."
  - Airborne: Vietnam Diary, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Vietnam Journal, 1969-1970, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
- Vietnam Scrapbook, 1969-1970; Series II; 1 partial reel microfilm (55 frames)
  This series consists of a microfilmed scrapbook. The scrapbook is divided into three sections: newspaper clippings, poetry, and documents. The newspaper clippings include articles and photographs from The "Airborne Screaming Eagle Newsletter" for the 101st Airborne Division and the "Pacific Stars and Stripes" Newspaper. Many articles have a connection to the O'Reilly Fire Support Base or other 101st Airborne Division-related activities. The articles are undated, but appear to be arranged in chronological order.
  The second section includes clippings of poetry from the "Pacific Stars and Stripes Newspaper," in addition to rough and final drafts of poems by H. David Cogley about Vietnam written between 1969 to 1970. The third section includes a hand-rendered map of South Vietnam with fire support base locations marked. There are also H. David Cogley's personal documents, including a transfer letter, an engineer checklist, duty list, and an after action report.
  - "Start", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/1)
  - "University of Montana Library", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/2)
  - "H. David Cogley Scrapbook", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/3)
  - "H. David Cogley Papers", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/4)
  - "Newspaper Clippings", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/5)
  - Airborne Screaming Eagle Newsletter; 101st Airborne Division (Airmobile), Vol. III, No. 23, Oct. 26, 1970; Headlines "101st Honored Avn. Unit of the Year," "U.S. Airpower Blasts Enemy; Cobras and Jets Record 37 Kills," "ARA Support Strong", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/6)
  - "U.S. Air Strikes Drive Reds Out of O'Reilly Area", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/7)
  - "Air Strikes Blast Attackers Around Embattled O'Reilly", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/8)
  - "Historical Battle Relived Along Perfume River", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/9)
  - "Minor Skirmishes Punctuate Lull," "Up We Go" photo of U.S. Army Chinook Helicopter," "Reds Attack ARVNS Near O'Reilly," "Accidental Mortar Explosion Kills 1 ARVN, Wounds 27", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/10)
  - "N. Viets Building New Supply Center in Laos," "ARVN, Reds Clash in 1 MR; U.S. Battle Action Scattered," "New VC Superstition: Black Cats are Fatal," "South Viets, NVA Dueling at O'Reilly", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/11)
  - "Red Ground Fire Downs 3 U.S. Helos Over Laos," "Reds Hit American Div. Posts, Fire 141 Rounds at O'Reilly," "Setting Up a Surprise for Charlie" (photograph), "ARVN on the Attack", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/12)
  - "ARVN, Militiamen Repel Attacks: 223 Reds Fall Near Quang Tri," "Judge Sees Fair Trial for Marine," "S. Viet Kills 38 As Reds Attack Near Fire Base," "No Streamlined Task" (photo), "Redlegs of the 101st Fire Howitzer at Suspected Enemy Positions About 25 mi. N. of Da Nang", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/13)
  - "There Was Lots to Like About Bob Hope But the Best Show Was the Girls" (photo, H. David Cogley pictured), "Viet Gunners Keep Battery Charged", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/14)
  - "Air Strikes Blast Attackers Around Embattled O'Reilly" (photo), 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/15)
  - "The Mosquito" a poem by Sgt. Roger A. Peters; "Misplaced Bomb Saves Embattled Troopers," "A Pronounced Trend: Some Military Units are Really Getting Short," "N. Viet. War Plan: Capture 2 Provinces," "Pilot Filmed in Death," "Children Harvest GI Gifts", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/16)
  - "Business As Usual Along the DMZ", South Vietnamese artilleryman near Fire Support Base O'Reilly (photo), "Alpha 4 Plays Eerie Game of Watch and Wait at DMZ" (political cartoon), 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/17)
  - "Calif. City Adopts Unit," Aug. 31, 1970, "GI Saved By Copter 'Life Belt'," Defensive wire at Firebase Tomahawk (photo), "Blood Tears Again Fill Street Without Joy," "Danger is Routine to Dustoff Crews", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/18)
  - "All Quiet in the Citadel" (photo),"Militiamen Fight to Regain 2 NVA-Overrun Hamlets" w/ photo, Helicopter landing at Fire Support Base O'Reilly (photo), "How Facts Point the Way: Air Spotting 'Barkys' Have Bite, Too", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/19)
  - "Now It's Fire Base Rubble" (photo), "The Last Few Hours at FSB Ripcord...We Just Hit the Ground and Prayed," "Reds Were Planning to Assault Firebase", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/20)
  - "Enemy Blasted in Ripcord-Like Hill Fight," "Out of Frying Pan, Into Fire for Never-Say Die Helo Scout," "Ripcord," "Retreat from Ripcord" Newsweek, Aug. 3, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/21)
  - "Retreat from Ripcord" continued, Duplicate articles, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/22)
  - "101st Near Ripcord", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/23)
  - Duplicate articles, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/24)
  - "AF Blazes NVA Trail" (photo), "Hot Battery in Action" (photo), 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/25)
  - "Battery in Action" (photo), "1 Man's Family in Cambodia" (photo), 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/26)
  - Eagles Aviation Units, photo clippings, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/27)
  - Photographs by 101st Info. Office, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/28)
  - Poems, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/29)
  - "Boondock Bards," Pacific Stars and Stripes, Newspaper, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/30)
  - "Boondock Bards," Pacific Stars and Stripes, Newspaper, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/31)
  - "Christian Objection," "The Soldier's Question," "Mankind Vindicated, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/32)
  - "Vision Lost," "Here in Vietnam," "Note on Passing," "Vision Lost" rough draft (Reel-frame 1/33)
  - "Note in Passing," Boarding Pass", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/34)
  - "Here in Vietnam", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/35)
  - "The Soldier's Question", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/36)
  - "Vision Lost", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/37)
  - "Christian Objection", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/38)
  - "Mankind Vindicated", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/39)
  - "Street Without Joy", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/40)
  - "Dream of Home", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/41)
  - Documents, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/42)
  - South Vietnam Fire Support Bases, (hand-rendered map), 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/43)
  - Transfer Letter for Herbert David Cogley, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/44)
  - Transfer Letter for Herbert David Cogley, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/45)
  - Transfer Letter for Herbert David Cogley, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/46)
  - Engineer inspection checklist, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/47)
  - Engineer inspection checklist, 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/48)
  - Operation Texas Star Combat After Action Report, (handwritten duty list), 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/49)
  - Combat After Action Report, Sept. 25, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/50)
  - Combat After Action Report, Sept. 25, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/51)
  - Combat After Action Report, Sept. 25, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/52)
  - Combat After Action Report, Sept. 25, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/53)
  - Combat After Action Report, Sept. 25, 1970 (Reel-frame 1/54)
  - "End", 1969-1970 (Reel-frame 1/55)
- Photographs, 1970; Series III; 50 items
  This series contains 50 frames of 35 mm flexible film negatives. These materials document some of David Cogley's experiences and travels during his Vietnam War military service. The images captured in these negatives provide insights into engineering practices and procedures applied to mobile military units during the conflict, equipment and base supplies for airborne units, daily base camp life for airborne personnel, and living conditions in cities near 101st Airborne Division central operations. Duplicate prints are available for viewing under photograph numbers 74-99 through 74-148.
  - Military Camp, 1970; 319(III)1 or 74-99 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Helicopter in hazy sky, 1970; 319(III)2 or 74-100 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - FSB (Fire Support Base) Rakkasan - NW of Hue. A CH54 flying crane, flying in a 105mm Howitzer. Most firebases had one or two batteries of 105 Howitzers, generally 6 guns per battery. Some fire bases had a battery of 155 mm guns also. Rakkasan had two batteries of 105 mm. Since all (except two) firebases in our area of operations were accessable only by air, the guns were always flown in either by this flying crane or the Chinook helicopter, genereally the latter, 1970; 319(III)3 or 74-101 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Fred Edwards and LZ team coming in, 1970; 319(III)4 or 74-102 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Squally pad, 1970; 319 (III)5 or 74-103 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - This sign was a personal project, 1970; 319(III)6 or 74-104 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - C-130 at Phu Bai, 1970; 319(III)7 or 74-105 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - C-130 Workhorse of Viet Nam. This was taken at Phu Bai, just out of hue, as I was leaving the country - DEROSing (DEROS, date of estimated return from overseas), 1970; 319(III)8 or 74-106 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Rest and money staging point at Da Nang, 1970; 319(III)9 or 74-107 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - MRS-100 8 cubic yard scrapper. I had three of these altogether while with the equipment platoon at Camp Eagle, 1970; 319(III)10 or 74-108 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - 3/4 ton dump truck, no other unit in the entire army has them. Air droppable one, thank God, 1970; 319(III)11 or 74-109 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Famous B-20 my private limousine, 1970; 319(III)12 or 74-110 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - B Company recreation, 1970; 319(III)13 or 74-111 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Camp Evans after a rocket hit the mess hall of the aviation unit in the background one evening, killing two and wounding several, 1970; 319(III)14 or 74-112 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Camp Evans, Sunday afternoon recreation, mandatory of course, 1970; 319(III)15 or 74-113 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - [Building a mess hall bunker] "Just about ready for the dozer", 1970; 319(III)16 or 74-114 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - [Building a mess hall bunker] "Had to backfill evenly. C Co. (not ours) backfilled a 10 foot by 20 foot mess hall bunker one side at a time. It was leaning severly before they decided they better start back filling the other side. They used it through, despite biterr complaints from the cooks who could hardly hang things from the walls, 1970; 319(III)17 or 74-115 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - On site bunker construction, 1970; 319(III)18 or 74-116 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Capt. Hell supervising, 1970; 319(III)19 or 74-117 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - [On site bunker construction--negative only, no original image description], 1970; 319(III)20 or 74-118 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Supports are generally 8 inches by 8 inches side and roof planks are 3 inches by 12 inches. Most of this lumber was shipped in from foreign countries, including the United States, 1970; 319(III)21 or 74-119 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - [A helicopter in the air with carrying a load.] "Meanwhile back at the ranch.", 1970; 319(III)22 or 74-120 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - 8 foot by 12 foot bunker headed for Rakassan. It will be placed in preapred pit, sided up, and buried, 1970; 319(III)23 or 74-121 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Hooking out bunker built at Camp Evans headed for Fire Station Base Rakassan. We sent out three different sizes: 10 foot by 24 foot, messhalls TOCs; 8 foot by 12 foot, squad size hutch; 6 foot by 8 foot, 3 to 4 man bunker, 1970; 319(III)24 or 74-122 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Purfume river at Hue, 1970; 319(III)25 or 74-123 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Perfume river at Hue, 1970; 319(III)26 or 74-124 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Streets of Hue, 1970; 319(III)27 or 74-125 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - View form the back of an army ambulence in Hue, 1970; 319(III)28 or 74-126 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Vietnamese taxi, 1970; 319(III)29 or 74-127 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Vietnamese taxi, 1970; 319(III)30 or 74-128 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Hue, 1970; 319(III)31 or 74-129 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Rice paddy north of Hue during the flood of November 1970, 319(III)32 or 74-130 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - The parachute was supposed to help the aerodynamics, but it never inflated. There was too much draft from the Chinook, 1970; 319(III)33 or 74-131 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Wreck at Squally Pad, Camp Evans, 1970; 319(III)34 or 74-132 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Chinook lifting out a wrecked Huey at Camp Evans, 1970; 319(III)35 or 74-133 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - This Heuy had justed picked up an LZ crew when a blade struck the tower at left as it was lifting off about 5 o'clock one morning. No one was injured, but a piece of the blade went through three walls of building before spending itself, 1970; 319(III)36 or 74-134 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - This dirt burn was constructed as a wall around this FSB. They are emplacing a drainage culvert here, 1970; 319(III)37 or 74-135 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - D-8 caterpillar. The only one in the division. We weren't authorized one as theywere not airmobile, but my platoon sergeant had scrounged this one all the way from..., 1970; 319(III)38 or 74-136 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Refugees in flood during November 1970. Many refused our rescue efforts, choosing instead to stayon the roofs of their houses which were inundated. Their tenacity was remarkabe, 319(III)39 or 74-137 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - B Company, 326 Engr. Bn., 101st Airborne Division. Lieutenant Ted Helminski, Lieutenant Sal Malquernero, Captian Ben Heil, Lieutenant Dave Cogley, Lieutenant Fred Edwards; Camp Evans, Summer, 1970; 319(III)40 or 74-138 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - David Cogley, extreme right, A moment of leisure at Camp Eagle, 101st HQ near Hue, 1970; 319(III)41 or 74-139 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Motor pool sergeants. Note the upright half-culvert. These are the urinals. Half barrels are inserted in a hole in the ground as receptacles, then diesel fuel poured in each day after use and ignited, to dispose of the residue. Same thing for fecal material, 1970; 319(III)42 or 74-140 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Lieutenant Salvatore Malguernero's sleeping area. Mosquito nets were mandatory, 1970; 319(III)43 or 74-141 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Case M450 very versatile fire base construction unit. Is flouwn out to FSB in one piece without disassembly. This is FSB Gladiator, west of Cam Evans, 1970; 319(III)44 or 74-142 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - 50 alibre machine gun, 4 barres. FSB Gladiator looking towrd FSB ripcord to west, 1970; 319(III)45 or 74-143 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Resupply bird, 1970; 319(III)46 or 74-144 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Resupply bird on Gladiator. Usually came in every other day or so with water, food, ammunition, replacement, but most important, MAIL. Note the LZ is ourside our main wire (perimeter), but insed a secondary perimeter. We had to mine sweep it each morning prior to use, 1970; 319(III)47 or 74-145 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Typical buncer 6 ft by 8 ft, buildt at Camp Evans and flown out. Three or four people bunked per bunker. This photo looking west from Gladiator, 1970; 319(III)48 or 74-146 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - FSB Gladiator, one battery of 105 mm Howitzers on top of a hill, 1970; 319(III)49 or 74-147 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - FSB Gladiator command post TOC (tactical operation center) looking southwest toward FSB Granite on top of mountain at center of picture, 1970; 319(III)50 or 74-148 (Box-folder 2/1)